Thanks so much.
Great to be here.
And Happy Halloween--
belated Halloween, everyone.
So I think the talk is going
to be split into two sections.
So I'll start by spending like
10 minutes, 15 minutes chatting
about transformers in general.
But I'm assuming most of
you are familiar with them
and we can move on to NPTs,
which Jannik and Neil will
be presenting.
So let's see, I'm going to try
to fly through the transformer
overview and maybe spend
a little bit extra time
on the history of
transformers and maybe just
tell the story a little bit.
I think that might
be more interesting.
So just in terms of the
transformer architecture,
the two kind of things that it
introduced for the first time
were multi-headed attention
and self-attention.
And then, it combined those with
fast autoregressive decoding.
So before the transformer,
pretty much everyone
was using LSTMs.
And LSTMs with attention.
But I'll try to get
into the difference
of self-attention,
multi-headed attention.
So originally, you
have two sequences
and you would have a attention
module, which would attend
from the source to the target.
And so, each token or each
word in the source sequence
would get associated with
a soft approximation of one
element in the target sequence.
And so, you'd end up
with something like this.
But with self-attention,
we did away
with the two separate sequences.
We make them both the same.
And so, you're relating each
element within the sequence
to another element
in the sequence.
And so, the idea
here is that you're
learning a relationship
of the words
within a sentence
to the other words.
So you can imagine something
like an adjective, which
is being applied to a noun.
And so you want to relate that
adjective-- like the blue ball,
you want to relate blue
as referring to ball.
So we're learning patterns
within the sequence--
intra-sequence patterns.
Sorry, I gave this
talk in Kenya.
So I'm using Swahili here.
But with multi-head
attention, the idea
is you have each
word represented
by an embedding, which is
in the depth dimension here.
And then, you have
your sentence of words.
You split that up into a
bunch of different groups.
So here, I've chopped it
depth-wise into four groups.
You apply attention to each one
of these groups independently.
And then, when you
get the result back,
you concatenate them together
and you're back to your model
dimension representation.
So what this lets you do is, if
each attention-- each attention
head can now focus on
learning one pattern.
So maybe attention head one
is learning the relationship
of adjectives to nouns.
And the second attention head
can learn something different.
So this lets us learn
a hierarchy or a list
of different relationships.
OK, so that was self-attention.
The other piece is fast
autoregressive decoding.
And do I really want
to go into this?
OK, I will.
So the important
thing about this
is that if you're doing normal
autoregressive decoding, what
you do is you generate
your first token.
And now, conditioned
on that first token,
you generate the second.
And conditioned on the first
two, you generate the third
and so on and so forth.
That's super slow, right?
It's a loop applying this
thing again and again.
And so, what we
can do instead is
we make an assumption
in the code
that our model always
generates the right thing.
And we generate-- and then,
we generate a prediction
only one token ahead.
And so, the way that
this looks is you--
OK, so y hat here--
sorry.
One second.
Input to output.
So you have your
outputs, which are y.
You have your targets,
which are y hat.
And what you do is you
feed in those gold targets
so that you don't need
to actually do this loop.
So instead of assuming--
instead of having
to generate the first
token, feed it back
into your architecture,
generate a second token,
you feed in the entire
target sequence.
And you just pretend that you
generate all the right tokens
up to position k.
And then, you predict
the k plus first.
And you compute
your loss on that.
And so in reality,
your model might
have generated at the
beginning of training junk.
But you're getting a
loss as if your model
had seen all the correct
tokens and is now just
predicting the next one.
This is a little
bit subtle, but it's
hugely impactful for training
speed because all of this
can be done in parallel.
And so, it's actually what
makes transformers so scalable.
OK, so in order to
do this successfully,
if you were just feeding in
all of the correct tokens
naively, what would
happen is your model
would just be able to look
forward in time and cheat.
So you've put in all of your
true targets, the things
that you're trying to get
your model to predict.
And so, if that's what you're
computing your loss on,
you could just look
forward in time
and say, OK, I'm just
going to grab that
and would get 0 error
trivially, right?
Because you've given it
all the right answers.
So what we have to do
inside the architecture
is we need to actually prevent
the attention mechanism
from being able to look at
tokens that it shouldn't
have been able to see already.
So the way that this
looks is you create a mask
on your attention.
And so, sorry,
this is the example
of doing a trivial attention.
If you don't mask your attention
properly, what it's going to do
is it's just going to
look into the future,
just grab the token that
you're telling it to predict,
and copy it over.
And so, it learns
something trivial.
Something it doesn't
actually generalize.
And so, what we
do is we actually
prevent it from attending
to those tokens.
We prevent it from
attending into the future.
For each position in
the source sequence,
we block out everything that
it shouldn't be able to see.
Everything into the future.
And then, as we move
down, we gradually
unblock so it can start
to see into the past.
So those are kind of the two--
the three major components
of transformers.
The self-attention, the
multi-head attention, and then,
deploying this gold targets--
decoding this fast
autoregressive decoding.
In terms of the
story, which might be
a little bit more interesting.
So transformers--
I was an intern
with Lukasz Kaiser at
Google back in 2017.
And I was sitting next
to Noam and she was
a couple of seats down from us.
And what's really incredible
is that, essentially,
this entire project came
together in like three months
and it was done.
So I showed up at Google.
Noam had been working on
autoregressive models.
Same thing with Ashish
and Jakab and Nikki.
And they had just been kind
of like exploring the space,
figuring it out.
And Lukasz and I,
at the same time,
we had been working on
this framework called
Tensor2Tensor,
which was explicitly
made for multimodal learning,
autoregressive learning.
And Lukasz is kind of
a master of keeping
track of everything that's
happening in the field
and adopting it.
And so, within
Tensor2Tensor there
were these emerging little
things that maybe one paper had
been written about and
people were interested in,
like LayerNorm but
it hadn't actually
taken off yet, the warm up in
the learning rate schedule.
All of these little
pieces were just default--
like on by default. And so,
when Noam and Ashish and Nikki
and Jakab came over and
adopted Tensor2Tensor,
all of these things were
just on by default. And so,
a lot of people, when they
look at the transformer paper,
it just seems like
there's so many
arbitrary little
things thrown in.
And now, in present day, these
have become standard for a lot
of different training
algorithms, like the learning
rate warm up, the
way that we did
initialization,
all of these pieces
have just become the norm.
But back then, they had kind
of just been introduced.
And so, we spent a lot of
time running ablations trying
to figure out which were
the necessary pieces
and what made it work.
And if any of you have actually
tried training transformers
and tried pulling
out the learning rate
warm up or changing any
of these little pieces,
you'll see that it really
does break down optimization.
It actually really
does hurt performance.
For instance, like removing the
LayerNorms, that type of thing.
I always thought it
was kind of funny how
all of these random additions
that Lukasz had just
thrown in because he was
playing around with them
turned out to be crucial, and
they were just on by default.
So anyway, it was
like three months.
I remember it all really
started coming together
towards the end, like just
before the NeurIPS deadline.
And I can still remember sitting
in the micro kitchen and Ashish
telling me-- like
it was just like--
I was a little intern.
Telling me like, this is
going to be such a big deal.
And I was like, yeah, sure, OK.
I have no idea what's happening.
I just showed up.
And he was like, no, dude,
like this actually matters.
We bumped up BLEU three points.
And I was like,
sick, great, anyway.
And then, I can
remember on the night
of the deadline for NeurIPS.
It was like 2:00 AM.
Ashish was the only
one left at the office
and we were still like
moving around figures
and adjusting things.
And then, I went to bed
but Ashish stayed up.
And I slept in like this
tiny little phone booth.
And then, for the other
paper that I was submitting,
I forgot to press Submit.
But luckily, some lady opened
the door to the phone booth
and hit me in the head while
I was sleeping in the morning.
And just before the
deadline I got the paper in.
And so, I owe it to
that lady for submitting
to NeurIPS that year.
But yeah, anyway, I think the
crazy thing about transformers
was that it all came together
in like three months.
Most of the ideas
happened in that span.
And it was just like this sprint
towards the NeurIPS deadline.
I think a lot of the other
members on the team, Jakab,
Lukasz, Noam, Ashish, they
knew how important it was.
But for me, I was
like, I don't know.
I really did not
appreciate the impact.
But in retrospect,
it's been amazing
how the community has kind of
come together and adopted it.
And I think most of
that can be ascribed
to the ease of optimization.
It seems like very robust
to hyperparameter choices.
So you don't need to tune
the hell out of it, spend
a lot of time tweaking
little things.
And the other side
is that it's super
tailored to the
accelerators that we run on.
So it's very paralyzable--
hyper-efficient.
And so, it lends
itself to that kind
of scaling law effort that's
really taken off in popularity.
OK, unless there
are any questions--
Yeah, that's a
fascinating story.
That was such a cool story.
Oh my God.
We're both excited, so we
just muted at the same time.
It's so cool.
Yeah, so that's my section.
If there's any questions,
happy to answer them.
Otherwise, let's get into NPTs.
NPTs are like, I think, they
are such a nice next level
abstraction of the architecture.
So you've probably seen
the trend of transformers
getting applied to new domains.
First into vision
and video and audio.
But this is kind of
like cutting back
to an even more abstract level.
I think tabular data.
I don't know.
I'll let Jannik and Neil
take over from here.
But I think NPT is a
pretty sick project.
Thanks, Aidan, for
the introduction.
Thanks all for the invitation.
We're very happy to be here.
And Neil and I are
now going to tell you
about our self-attention
between datapoints paper
where we just introduced the
non-parametric transformer
architecture.
We'll start with a
little bit of motivation,
move on to explaining the
architecture in detail,
then show you the experiments.
This is more or less a
step through of the paper,
but maybe, with a little bit of
extra insight here and there.
All right, as promised, the
motivation, a brief summary.
So we'll start by thinking about
something that we don't often
think about, and that is that
from CNNs to transformers,
most of supervised
deep learning relies
on parametric prediction.
So what that means is that we
have some set of training data.
And we want to learn to predict
the outcomes y from the inputs
x.
And first, we set up some model
with tunable parameters theta.
Then, we optimized
these parameters
to maximize predictive
likelihoods on a training set
or, equivalently, we
minimize the loss.
And then, after training,
we have this optimized set
of parameters theta.
And then, at test time, we
just put these into the model
and use these parameters to
predict on novel test data.
And so, crucially here,
our prediction at test time
only depends on these
parameters, right?
It's parametric.
Also, that means that
given these parameters,
the prediction is entirely
independent of the training
data.
And so, why would we want
to do parametric prediction?
Well, it's really convenient.
Because all that we've
learned from the training
data can be summarized
in the parameters.
And so, at prediction
time, we only
need these final
parameters and we do not
need to store the
training data, which
might be really, really large.
On the other hand,
we usually have
models that already
predict for a bunch of data
in parallel, right?
Think of mini batching
and modern architectures.
And actually, things
like batch norm
already make these
data interact.
And so, our thinking
here was that if we've
got all of this data
in parallel anyways,
there's no reason not
to make use of it.
And so, more a bit grander, we
challenge parametric prediction
as the dominant paradigm
in deep learning.
And so, we want to give models
the additional flexibility
of using the training
data directly
when making predictions.
And so, a bit more
concretely, we
introduced the non-parametric
transformer architecture.
And this is going to be
a general deep learning
architecture, meaning
we can apply it
to a variety of scenarios.
NPTs will take the entire data
set as input whenever possible.
And NPTs then, crucially, learn
to predict from interactions
between data points.
And to achieve this, we use
multi-head self-attention
that, as Aidan has
introduced us to,
has just really established
itself as the general purpose
layer for reasoning.
We also take another thing
from the NLP community
and we use a stochastic
masking mechanism.
And we use that to tell NPTs
where to predict, and also
to regularize the
learning task of it.
And lastly, of course,
we hope to convince you
that this ends up
working really well
and that this simple
idea of learning
to predict from the other
datapoints of the input,
from the training
points of the input,
and supporting them as well.
Sorry.
And so, very briefly summarizing
what we've heard already.
A, we input into NPTs
the entire data set.
And then, B, let's say, for
the purpose of this slide here,
we only care about predicting
the orange question
mark in that green row.
And then, we can compare NPTs
to parametric prediction, right?
So a classical
deep learning model
would predict this
target value only
from the features of
that single green input.
To do that, it would use
the parameters theta.
Those would depend
on whatever training
data we've seen and so on.
But at test time, we only look
at that single row for which
we care about the prediction.
In contrast, NPTs predict
an explicit dependence
on all samples in the input.
They can look beyond that
single gradation of interest.
And look at all other
[INAUDIBLE] that are there
and consider their
values for prediction.
So this presents an
entirely different way
of thinking about how we
learn predictive mechanisms.
And somebody on Twitter
called this k-NN 2.0,
which we would have not
written in the paper.
But maybe it is
kind of a nice way
of thinking about how
NPTs can learn to predict.
So of course, non-parametric
models are a thing already.
We didn't invent them at all.
And I define them
here as prediction
in explicit dependence on
the training data, which
is certainly what NPTs do.
Classical examples,
like Gaussian processes,
k nearest neighbor,
kernel methods,
those might be familiar to you.
And there exists, also,
efforts to combine
the benefits of non-parametric
metrics and representation
learning in a similar fashion
to how we did it in NPTs.
However, these approaches are
usually limited, in some sense,
in comparison to NPTs, right?
They're often kind of motivated
from the statistics community
a bit more.
They often requires some
more finicky approaches,
such as inference
schemes or are limited
in the interactions they can
learn or things like that.
And so, we really think
NPTs present maybe
the most versatile
and most widely
applicable of these
non-parametric prediction
approaches.
That's something we
explicitly wanted to have.
We wanted to have something
that's really easy to use, plug
and play, works in
a ton of scenarios,
and works really well.
And so, with that,
I'll hand over
to Neil, who's going
to tell you about
the non-parametric transformer
architecture in all
of its details.
We also have one question.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Go ahead.
Hi, Jannik.
Hi.
So, could you please go
back to the previous slide?
The very previous slide??
Yes, yes.
This slide, yeah.
So in terms of the
problem definition,
I think it is quite similar
to some meta learning
problem, which basically
learns a mapping from a data
point on the data set
to some predictions.
So could you please
suggest any differences
between your problem setting and
meta learning problem settings.
I can't really figure out any
differences between these two
problems.
Well, I think it really
depends on the framing
that you want to have, right?
So I would say
meta learning would
be when I try to predict
over multiple data sets.
So when I try to
predict some-- when
I try to learn some
sort of prediction model
where I can just plug
in a different data
set and it will automatically--
or almost automatically
give me new predictions on this
different data distribution.
But that's not what
we do at all, right?
We are training a single
model for a fixed data set.
And so, this is why
I wouldn't really
call that meta learning
because we're doing--
we're trying to print
on the same tasks
that all the supervised
deep learning
or any supervised
machine learning method
is trying to predict well on.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Okay, so assuming you use
kind of same test site
to test your training
model, right?
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
I mean like-- so basically,
in meta learning,
we're going to test on different
kind of meta test sets.
But in your case,
you just want to use
a test set which is
similar to the distribution
of your training set.
Is that right?
Yeah, absolutely.
So we explore data set
distribution shift a bit.
I think it's a really
interesting scenario.
I think meta learning
different data sets
is also an interesting
scenario, right?
When you have this model
where you could just
push in different data sets.
But for the scope of this
paper, it's very much
training set, test
set, they come
from the same distribution.
And we're just trying to
do supervised learning
in a standard setting.
I see.
Cool.
Thank you.
Thank you for the question.
Yeah, and I would chime in a
couple of additional things,
I guess.
So at least from what I
understand from the problem
definition of meta learning, I
think the aim is more, perhaps,
being able to perform well on a
new data set with a relatively
small number of
additional gradient steps
on that data set.
So I think there are some
interesting ways that you could
actually consider applying
NPTs in a meta learning
type setting.
And so we'll get into
this a little bit more.
But for example, there might
be ways to, essentially,
add in a new data set.
So let's suppose we've trained
on a bunch of different data
sets.
We now add in a new data set.
We can, perhaps, do some sorts
of zero shot meta learning,
basically, where there's no need
for additional gradient steps
because we're
basically predicting
kind of similar to how you might
do prompting nowadays in NLP
literature.
Anyways, yeah, I think we'll
get into some more details.
Just to chime in on that.
I don't think that every
meta learning algorithm--
I think the one that
you're describing right now
are optimization based, but
they're also black box ones.
You don't need to further--
I think the main
difference seems
to be that there is one task
versus multiple tasks for meta
learning.
Yeah, I think so, too.
I think that the main-- yeah,
the main framing question
is whether or not there's
multiple data sets.
Cool.
OK, awesome.
If there's no other
questions, I'll
dive a bit more into
the architecture.
Awesome.
So there's three key
components to NPTs.
I'm going to first state
them at a high level.
And then, we'll go through
each of them in more detail.
So first of all, we take
the entire data set.
All data points as input.
So for example, at
test time, the model
is going to take as input
both training and test data.
And we approximate this with
mini batches for large data.
We apply self-attention
between data points.
So for example, at test
time, we model relationships
amongst training points,
amongst test points,
and between the two sets.
And then, finally, we have
this masking-based training
objective.
It's a BERT-like
stochastic masking.
And the key point
is that we actually
use it on both features as
well as on training targets.
And we'll get into
why that leads
to an interesting
predictive mechanism later.
So to start with, this
idea of data sets as input.
There's two things that
compose the input to NPT.
It's a full data set
in the form of a matrix
X and a masking matrix
M. And so, Jannik
has described this data
set matrix a little bit.
We basically have
data points as rows.
The columns are attributes.
And each attribute shares
some kind of semantic meaning
among all of its data points.
So say, for example, you're
just doing single target
classification or regression.
The last column
would be the target,
and the rest of the matrix
would be input features.
So for example, the
pixels of an image.
We also have a masking matrix.
So let's say, we're thinking
about mask language modeling.
The mask tokens
will just tell us
where we're going
to conceal words
and where we're going
to backpropagate a loss.
We do a similar type
of thing here where
we use this binary
mask matrix to specify
which entries are masks.
And the goal is to
predict masked values
from observed values.
I see that there was a
question about handling inputs
with different lengths.
In the data sets
we've considered,
we'll get into it in
the results section,
but it's mostly been sort
of tabular and image data
where the lengths for each of
the data points is the same,
but it would work
just like padding.
That would be a reasonable
way to go about that.
And there's also kind of
an interesting-- yeah.
Go for it, Jannik.
Just to add to that.
I'm not sure if length refers
to columns or to rows, right?
Rows we don't care
about how many rows.
Length, padding or something
would be an option.
Yeah, my question was
about columns exactly.
So that makes sense.
Thanks.
Yeah, I mean, that goes along
with the whole meta earning
discussion is, I
think, if we wanted
to adapt two data sets that
have a different number of data
points per data set, we can
take advantage of the fact
that self-attention
is OK with that.
Cool.
So continuing on.
Left to discuss
here is, basically,
how we do the embedding.
So to put this
more explicitly, we
have this data matrix that has
n data points, it's called X.
And it also has d attributes.
And we have this
binary mask matrix M.
We're going to stack them.
And then, we're going to
do a linear embedding.
So specifically, we're doing
the same linear embedding
independently for
each data point.
We're learning a different
embedding for each attribute.
We have a positional encoding
on the index of the attributes
because we don't
really care about, say,
being equivariant
over the columns.
If it's tabular
data, you, of course,
want to treat all these kind
of heterogeneous columns
differently.
And then, finally, we have an
encoding on the type of column,
so whether or not it's
continuous or categorical.
And that ends up giving us this
input data set representation
that is dimensions n by d by e.
The second key component
of NPTs is the attention
between data points.
So to do that, we first take
this representation we have
and flatten to an n by d
times e representation.
So basically, we're treating
each of these d times
e size rows as if it's
a token representation.
We're actually going to just
accomplish this operation using
multi and self-attention.
We've reviewed this a lot.
But the nice thing is that we
know from language modeling,
if we stack this
multiple times, we
can model these higher
order dependencies.
And here, they're
between data points.
And that's really the key
draw of this architecture.
There's been other instances of
people using attention verse--
for similar sorts of things.
So for example, like
attentive neural processes.
A lot of times they've sort
of use just a single layer
as kind of a
representational lookup.
And we believe that
this, actually,
ends up limiting expressivity.
And that by stacking
this many times,
you can learn more complex
relationships between the data
points.
Neil, you also have
some questions.
You can go ahead first.
Oh, cool.
Thanks.
I have a question about how
you guys do the embedding.
Is it always like-- or do
we use convolutional filters
or linear layers?
What is the type of
embedding that you guys use?
Yeah, so I'm attempting
to go back to the slide.
I think it's not very
happy with me right now.
But yeah, so for tabular data,
we did just linear embeddings,
actually.
So we could get into, I guess,
details of featurization
for categorical and continuous.
But it's literally like,
say, for categorical, you
do a one hot encoding.
And then, you learn
this embedding that
is specific to that attribute.
And then, for
numerical, I believe,
we were just
standard normalizing.
For the image
data, we did end up
using a ResNet 18
encoder for CIFAR-10.
However, I think that--
I mean, we'll discuss that
a bit later in results.
But that embedding
is a bit arbitrary.
You can sort of do whatever.
The key part of the
architecture is the attention
between data points.
In terms of how you actually
want to embed each attribute,
it's kind of up to you.
Thanks.
I think [AUDIO OUT]
another question.
Same question as Victor's.
Awesome.
Cool.
So here we have attention
between data points done.
So we can also do this
attention between attributes.
So we reshape back to this
n by d by e representation.
And then, we can just apply
self-attention independently
to each row.
In other words, to
a single data point.
And the intuition for why
we would do this nested type
idea where we switch between
attention between data points
and attention
between attributes is
just we're trying to learn
better per data point
representations for the between
data point interactions.
This is literally just
normal self-attention
as you'd see in language
modeling or image
classification.
The attributes are
the tokens here.
And finally, we just
rinse and repeat.
So what are we actually
getting out of this?
To summarize, we're learning
higher order relationships
between data points.
We're learning transformations
of individual data points.
And then, importantly, NPT is
equivariant to a permutation
of the data points.
This basically just
reflects the intuition
that the learned relationships
between the data points
should not depend on the
ordering in which you
receive them or in which
you observe your data set.
The third key component of NPT
is a masking-based training
objective.
So recall that what
we're trying to do
is we're trying to
predict missing entries
from observed entries.
And those mass values can
be both features or targets.
So again, the classic use, say,
of masked language modeling
is to do
self-supervised learning
on a sequence of
tokens, which you
could think of as just having
features in our setting.
Ours is a bit
different in that we
do stochastic feature masking
to mask feature values
with a probability
p sub feature.
And then, we also do this
masking of training targets
with this probability
p sub target.
So if we write out the
training objective,
we are just taking a weighted
sum of the negative log
likelihood lost from targets
as well as from features.
And of course, at
test time, we're
only going to mask and compute
a loss over the targets of test
points.
So to break this down a
bit further and point out
some of the cool
parts of it here,
the thing that's highlighted
right now on the far right
is the term relating
to the features.
It's the feature masking.
Basically, we find that this
has a nice regularizing effect.
More or less, the model
can now predict anywhere.
It makes the task a bit harder
and introduces some more
supervision.
And we found in an ablation for
the tabular data sets that it
helped for 8 of 10 of those.
And then, there's
this other term,
which is kind of interesting.
It's the stochastic
target masking.
And the idea is
that you're actually
going to have some
training targets unmasked
to the model at input
at training time, which
means that the NPT
can learn to predict
the masked targets of
certain training data points
using the targets of
other training data points
as well as all of the
training features.
And so, that means
you don't actually
need to memorize a mapping
between training inputs
and outputs in your parameters.
You can, instead, devote the
representational capacity
of the model to learn functions
that use other training
features and targets as input.
So this is kind of getting
into the idea of this sort
of learn k-NN idea.
Obviously, we can learn more
complex relational lookups
and those sorts of
things from this.
But you can imagine
one such case being--
we have a bunch of test
data points coming in
and we're going to
look at their features
and use that to assign them
to clusters of training data
points.
And then, our prediction
for those points
is just going to be an
interpolation of the training
targets in that
respective cluster.
That's an example of
something that this mechanism
lets NPTs learn.
All right, so if
there's any questions,
we can take them now.
Otherwise, happy to take them
in the discussion or something.
All right, so let's discuss--
Yeah, go for it.
I'm curious, when you are
using the entire data set,
is that limited type
of data sets you
can use because of the size?
Yeah, so in practice,
we do random mini
batching as an approximation.
So the idea is just--
if you have a reasonably
large mini batch,
you're going to benefit
a bit from still
having this look up ability.
Because in a reasonable
number of classes,
probably, you're going
to be able to learn
some interesting mappings
based on features and targets
amongst those classes.
We found, in practice, that--
and we'll get into
this a little bit.
But we do actually,
indeed, learn
to use relationships between
data points on prediction
for data sets where we're
doing mini batching.
And we also didn't,
necessarily, find
that you need like a ludicrously
large batch size for this
to be a thing.
But I do think
it's just this is,
in general, an important point.
And it's one that points
us towards looking
into, say, sparse
transformers literature
if we're trying to expand
to some larger data sets
without having the mini
batching assumption.
Great, thank you.
If I can add a number to that.
We can, without mini batching,
accommodate data sets
of around 8,000 points or so.
So that already accounts for a
fair proportion, I would say,
of the tabular data
sets out there.
But we also do data sets
with 11 million points
where, obviously, we then
resort to mini batching.
So that's very good to
have an idea of the sizes
that we're talking about.
I'm curious on that.
I mean, it is pretty exciting.
I feel like you don't normally
hear about transformers being
applied to it as a size 8,000.
I'm curious-- we can talk
about this sort of later
once we've covered the
new material-- if you
found that sample efficiency
is one of the key gains here?
Or just experience
working on small data sets
of transformers, generally?
And yeah, but I'll happy
to punt the answer to that
until after this part
of the discussion.
Yeah, I think that'd be really
nice to talk about a bit.
And it was something that,
in general, I guess, I'd
say it was surprising to us in
terms of how robust NPTs were
on small data sets and
how we surprisingly
didn't have to tune a
terrible number of parameters.
But we can get into
details in a bit.
Awesome.
So to get into the
experiments, we
focused a lot on tabular
data because it's
a very general setting.
And it's also notoriously
challenging for deep learning.
So we know tree-based boosting
methods, stuff like XGBoost,
is very dominant.
And this is also a very
relevant domain to, I think,
people in industry and
that sort of thing.
So we were excited
about the idea
of trying to do better on this.
So we chose a broad
selection of data
sets varying across a
few different dimensions.
As we mentioned, on the order
of hundreds to tens of millions
of instances.
Broad range of the number of
features and the composition
of features in terms of being
categorical or continuous.
Various types of tasks,
binary or multi-class
classification as
well as regression.
And like I said,
the baselines were
kind of the usual
suspects for tabular data.
XGBoost, CatBoost, LightGMB,
tune MLPs, and TabNet,
which is a transformer
architecture for tabular data.
So to get into the
results, here, I'm
showing the average rank
for the various subtasks.
We did well in terms of
rank-wise performance
against methods like
CatBoost and XGBoost,
which are designed
specifically for tabular data.
And in fact, we find that
NPT is the top performer on 4
of the 10 of these data sets.
On image data, I mentioned
that we used a CNN encoder.
And with that, we were
performing well on CIFAR-10.
And we also think that,
in general, like with,
let's say new work on image
transformers and small data,
this can probably just be
done with linear patching.
And so, this-- the manner in
which you're embedding things
is probably not the key.
Neil, if I can jump
in with two questions.
Can you go back
two slides first?
One is just a small minor point.
Back one more, please.
Thank you.
Here for the features, 50 plus.
What does plus mean here?
I'll have to double check
what the exact number is.
I'm pretty sure it's
probably around 50.
I would guess like--
So the 50 is really an order of.
It's not like 150 or 5,000.
Yeah, I mean, I'll double
check for you or you
can check with the
metadata statistics
at the end of the paper.
But no, it wasn't
arbitrarily large.
I would say, though, we
did these ablations on
whether or not we actually need
attention between attributes.
We did find that this
ended up benefiting us.
But you could, perhaps, do
say just an MLP embedding
in that dimension and go to
like a relatively small number
of hidden dimensions and
fit kind of an arbitrary
number of features.
So I think that--
yeah, if you kind of relax
the necessity of attention
between attributes,
you can probably
scale out, at least at that
dimension, quite a lot.
OK, and then, my
second question, if you
could go forward one slide.
Oh, thank you.
Here, I'm not sure
I quite caught.
What is 4 of 10 data sets, 2 of
10 data sets, and 4 of 10 mean?
This is of all the tabular
data sets that we had.
Oh, I see, so you're saying
binary classification is 4.
I see.
OK.
Yeah, exactly.
Awesome.
Any other questions?
The standard errors here.
Because I mean, there's
just 10 data sets, right?
Yeah, correct.
10 total tabular data sets.
Yeah.
But these are--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Yeah, these are
rank-wise performance.
Correct.
OK, I'm just missing how the--
where the uncertainty comes
from in this case.
Yeah, averaged over 4 of
10 data sets, the rank.
So for each particular
data set, we
have a rank of all
the different methods.
Then, we take the average
and the variant answer
of the rankings within
each of the types of task--
within binary classification,
within multiclass, et cetera.
Got it.
We also, if you're curious, have
the full results in the paper.
Yeah, thank you.
We also have a couple
of questions more.
And some more
questions [INAUDIBLE]..
Hey, yeah, thanks.
I guess, I just found
it a little surprising
that the worst
performer was k-NN given
that it's also non-parametric.
I guess, could you
comment on that?
Is it that there's something
intrinsic to the NPT that
makes it just exceptional far
beyond other non-parametric
methods?
Yeah, why is it that k-NN
performs the worse here?
Well, I suppose,
ultimately, k-NN
is still a relatively
naive predictive method
in that it might
just be predicting
based on cluster means.
So for example, I think this
is probably universally true
for all the data sets,
but there's probably
some amount of kind of
additional reasoning
that needs to occur over
the features, at least,
at a basic level.
So for example, one
of the data sets
is this poker hand
data set where
it's like a mapping between
all of the different hands
you have in poker and
what like they're commonly
known to people, like
full houses or whatever.
So this requires some amount
of reasoning over the features
to be able to group
things together.
So just taking the cluster
means of the featurization
of those different
hands is likely not
going to give you a great
predictive function.
Whereas, NPTs can kind of do
the classic thing where, say,
you have an MLP type of
thing over the features
or a tree type of thing
over the features.
You can learn some sort
of complex embedding.
But then, you also can do
some non-parametric sort
of prediction based on, say,
like clusters of embeddings.
Yeah, that makes sense.
I guess, what if you used
pre-trained embeddings
from a stack of encoders as
your vector representation
for the k-NN?
How do you think that
would perform compared
to the rest of the crowd?
Yeah, yeah, so this is like--
I mean, this idea is
kind of like deep kernel
learning where like--
Yeah, I believe it is
deep kernel learning.
It is, basically, you
use an MLP independently.
So you learn an MLP on
each input data point.
And then, you apply a GP
over all the representations
of those.
So you get this complex
embedding and then the lookups.
The key difference between
that type of idea and NPTs
is that we also learn the
relationships between the data
points themselves because we
use this parametric attention
mechanism to learn
the relationship.
So we're not just learning like
an embedding independently,
we're, basically,
backpropagating
through the entire process
learning the ways in which we
would try to embed this.
But also, the ways that
say the lookup would occur
and, essentially, the
relationships that
can potentially be kind
of higher order as well.
OK, cool.
Wait.
Might I ask one
more follow-up or--
Yeah, go for it.
Cool.
Yeah, thanks.
So I guess, then, if
the advantage of NPT
has to do with sort of the
relationships between data
points, then what if you
took the-- let's say encoder
representations and then
you pass that as input, say,
for the ten nearest neighbors
along with some other input
representation and sort of
had this weighted average
like attention style
where you weighted
the vectors of the
nearest neighbors based
on the attention weights
between those input data points
and then the supplied
input data point.
And then, like pass that as the
vector to the final prediction
later.
Do you think that captures some
amount of the relationship?
Or is that off base?
So I think the nice part--
and really, what
our idea is behind
this whole thing is just
these sorts of instances
where certain
fixed kernels would
perform particularly well on
tasks is kind of an annoyance.
And ultimately, tuning a
lot of these types of things
or trying to derive the
predictive methods that
might make a lot of sense for a
given situation kind of stinks.
And ideally, you'd want to just
back propagate on a data set
and kind of learn these
relationships yourself.
So I, actually, would be
really interested to see
if we can come up with some
synthetic experiments that
have these very particular
k-NN like predictive mechanisms
and just see if we can
learn precisely those
and get 0 error with NPTs.
And in fact, we'll get
into this a little bit
with some of the interventional
experiments we do.
We have precise lookup
functions that NPTs end up
being able to learn.
So we can learn interesting
relational functions.
Cool.
Yeah.
Thanks a lot.
Appreciate it.
All right.
One more question from--
Yeah, sure.
I just want to clarify
something about--
basically, so at
test time, you just
take the exact same
data set and you just
add your test examples, right?
And then, you do the
same type of masking.
Is that how it works?
Yeah, correct.
OK, got it.
And I do have one more question.
That is just because I
think I misunderstood how
the effects of
your NPT objective.
Do you mind going
back to that slide?
Sure.
Yeah, can you
repeat one more time
what makes this so special?
Yeah, so the regularizer on
the right over the features
I would think of very similarly
to self-supervised learning
with just a standard
transformer.
You're basically
just introducing
a lot more supervision.
Even if, say, you're just
doing a supervised objective,
this is kind of some amount of
reconstruction over the feature
as you learn a more
interesting representation
and what a regularizing effect,
which we think is interesting.
But perhaps, not as interesting
as this stochastic target
masking.
This one is unique
because in kind
of standard parametric
deep learning,
you're not going to have an
instance in your training
process where you're
taking targets as input.
And so, basically,
what happens is
if you have your training data
set as input, whatever, you're
going to have some stochastic
feature masking stuff happening
on the features.
Amongst the training
targets, you're randomly
going to have some of those
unmasked and some of them
will indeed be masks.
You're going to be
back propagating
a loss on the ones that are
masked, of course, because you
don't want your model to
have those available at input
if you're going to actually try
to back propagate a loss on it.
But you can use the
other ones as input.
And that means you
can learn these kind
of like interpolative functions.
So that was this
whole idea of being
able to kind of learn k-NN.
But doesn't that allow
the model to cheat again?
Yeah, so this is an
interesting point.
And actually, subtle.
So I think it's really
worthwhile to bring up.
So first of all, we never
actually back propagate a loss
on something that was visible
to the model at input.
And so, if, for example, the
model did actually end up,
basically, overfitting
on training labels,
we would not observe
the model's ability
to generalize to test data.
We don't observe this.
So obviously, it
seems like this kind
of blocking of back
propagation on labels
that are visible at input
to the NPT is helping.
It could also be possible
that in BERT style
stochastic masking,
you also randomly will
flip some labels to be
in a different category.
So this is kind of
just like a random fine
print that was introduced
in the BERT masking text.
We also do that.
So it's possible that
somehow contributes to that.
But it's probably pretty
likely to just be the fact
that we're not back propagating
a loss on something that's
visible.
Great.
Thanks.
Makes sense.
I have two more questions
if I can jump in.
Yeah, sure.
Sorry, can we go to the
metrics, the performance,
the results slide.
Sure.
I feel like I missed
something else.
I'm sorry about this.
So looking on the binary
classification, AUROC.
Can you clarify what
these numbers mean?
Are they the AUROC?
So this is the--
so on each of the data sets--
so say, for a particular
binary classification data set,
we're going to get a
ranking of the methods.
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Repeat this.
Yeah.
Go for it.
So these numbers here are
the relative ranking across,
in this particular case,
the four data sets.
Correct.
Yeah.
Oh, I see.
So these values
are not the AUROCs
on average across the data sets.
No.
Yeah they're not--
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Averaging AUROC
might make sense,
but averaging things
like accuracy and RMSE
seems like a bad idea, right?
Because you might
have some data sets
where everything
is high accuracy
or where RMSE needs something
drastically different.
I see.
So these numbers here only
tell us the relative ranking
between the different methods,
not how well they actually
perform.
I mean, it's also probably
how they perform relative
to one another, but not how
will they perform [INAUDIBLE]..
I see.
That's all in the appendix.
We have that information.
I see.
OK, I was sitting here confused
going like, why is AUROC?
Why is the best
one the smallest?
And accuracy?
What is an accuracy of 2.5?
Anyways.
OK, that makes much more sense.
Thank you both.
Awesome.
Great.
So I'll try to
speed through this
just in the interest of time.
But basically,
the thing that you
might be thinking after
all of these results
is, are we even learning
any data point interactions
on these real data sets?
And so, basically, we
designed an experiment
to figure this out.
And the idea is that we're
going to disallow NPT
from using other data points
when predicting on one of them.
If we do that and we
observe that NPT actually
predicts or performed
significantly worse,
it is, indeed, using
these interactions
between data points.
A subtle challenge or
just an added bonus
we can get from this is that,
ideally, we wouldn't actually
break batch statistics.
So let's say the mean of
each particular attribute,
if we can find a way to
do this experiment such
that we don't
break these things,
we can rule out the possibility
that we learn something that's
a bit similar to batch norm.
And so, the way that we
do this is we basically
look at the predictions
for each one
of the data points in sequence.
So let's say, in
this case, we're
looking at the
prediction of the model
for this particular green row.
And it's going to be predicting
in this last column that
has this question
mark, which is masked.
What we're going to
do is we're going
to permute each
of the attributes
independently amongst
all other data points
except for that one.
So the information for
that row, if it was just
predicting a classic parametric
deep model, is still intact.
But the information from all
of the other rows is gone.
So this is why we call this sort
of the corruption experiment.
And so, we find,
in general, when
we perform this experiment,
performance kind of
falls off a cliff for the vast
majority of these methods.
And I'll note that
the performances
between the methods on a lot
of these were fairly close.
And so, this is, actually,
indeed, pretty significant.
So for example, on
protein, we went
from being the top performer
amongst all the methods
to the worst performer.
Worse than even like k-NN
or something like that.
I'll also note that there's kind
of this interesting behavior
where on these data sets like
Forest and Kick and Breast
Cancer.
We actually observed
that there is, basically,
no drop in performance.
And we, basically, see this as
kind of an interesting feature
and not necessarily a
bug of the model, which
is that if we're backpropagating
on a given data set,
the model can sort of just
find that it's actually not
that worthwhile to
attempt to predict using
some kind of relational
predictive mechanism
amongst data points.
And can instead just learn
to predict parametrically.
And, basically,
ignore other data
points when it's predicting
on any given one of them.
And so, this probably leads
to some interesting ideas
where perhaps you could
do, like, post doc pruning
or something like that.
Taking away the attention
between data points
and doing fine
tuning, let's say.
All right, so now I'll
hand over to Jannik
talk a bit about learning some
interesting relationships.
Yeah, will you, though?
I see that we're at the
end of what the time is.
But I know there's a buffer
planned in or something.
Can you-- I can go
through this experiment.
We can have a bit of discussion.
What do you guys prefer?
Yeah, I think,
normally, what we do
is we would sort of stop
the recording at this point
and have an off the
record discussion.
And I guess the question
to ask is, does anyone have
any questions at this point?
But I think we've basically
been watching questions
as they come.
So I personally feel fine
just considering the sorts
of questions throughout.
Yeah, I guess that
sounds good, Jannik.
You can go forward
with it as planned.
And yeah.
Later we can see
about the time thing.
I think this will only be like
another four or five minutes.
Yeah, that's for sure.
Then go for it.
Yeah, for sure.
All right, so Neil has
now told us how well
NPTs perform in real data.
And that they do make use of
information from other samples
to the input.
But we're now going
to take this a bit
further and come up with some
toy experiments that test a bit
the extent to which NPTs can
learn to look up information
from other rows.
The extent to which
they can learn
this non-parametric
prediction mechanism.
And so, specifically,
what we'll do
is we'll create the following
semi-synthetic data set.
So I want you to focus on A now.
So we take one of
the tabular data
sets that we've used previously,
specifically, the protein data
set, but it doesn't
really matter.
What matters is that it's
a regression data set.
And so, now, what we do is we--
the top half here is
the original data set.
But the bottom half is a
copy of the original data
set where we have unveiled
the true target value.
And so, now, NPTs
could learn to use
attention between data
points to achieve arbitrarily
good performance.
They could learn to
look up the target
values in these
matching duplicate rows.
And then, paste them back into
that masked out target value.
Then, at test
time, of course, we
put in a novel test data input
where this mechanism is also
possible just to make
sure that it hasn't
learned to memorize anything.
But it has, actually, learned
this correct relational
mechanism.
And so, what we see
is that, indeed, NPTs
do successfully learn
to perform this lookup.
So what I'm visualizing
here is attention maps.
And they very clearly
show that, let's say,
when predicting for
this green row here,
this first green row,
what NPTs look at
is exactly only that
other green row here.
And so, this is really nice.
We can further look at the
kind of the Pearson correlation
between what NPTs should
predict and what they actually
do predict.
And so, this is 99.9%.
This is much better
than anything
you could achieve with
parametric prediction.
And so, it seems that
NPTs here can actually
discover this mechanism.
And discover, here, I feel
like is the right word.
Because NPTs could
have, as we've seen,
just also continue to predict
in parametric fashion,
right, from each
row independently.
This is really kind
of showing to us
that there is this bias
in the model to learn
to predict from other rows.
And of course, that is also
very attractive in this setting
because it allows you to
achieve arbitrary low loss
in this setting, or as low
as you can optimize for it.
And so, we kind of
take that to mean
that our gradient-based
discovery
non-parametric philosophy
seems to make some sense.
And so, we can take this a bit
further by performing somewhat
of an interventional
experiment that investigates
the extent to which NPTs
have actually learned
a robust causal mechanism
that's underlying
this semi-synthetic data set.
And so, just appending this
extra column of test data.
That's already kind of cool.
But I think we can
take it a bit further
and actually study if this
generalizes beyond the data
that we see in the
training set or beyond data
coming from this
specific distribution.
And so, what we now
do is we intervene
on individual duplicate
data points at test time
by varying their target value.
So now, we only care about the
prediction in a specific row.
We do this across all rows.
But at each time, we just
care about a single row.
What we do is we change
the target value here.
What we're hoping to see is
that the NPT just adjusts
the prediction as well, right?
There's a very simple
intervention experiment for us
to test if NPTs have actually
learned this mechanism.
And to some extent, it
also tests robustness.
Because now, we're
associating target values
with features that are not part
of the training distribution
here.
And so, what we see is that as
we adjust these values here,
this is the duplicate value.
And then, we here see
that the target value--
as we adjust them, we can
see that the correlation
stays really, really good.
It's not quite 99.9%,
like on average.
We're now at 99.6%.
But it's still very, very good.
And at this point, you might
be slightly annoyed with me
because standard
non-parametric models can also
solve this task, right?
But this is a task that I could
solve by nearest neighbors.
Sure, maybe, I would have to
change the input format a bit
because this is kind of
like in a batch setting
and I can just use masks.
But most generally,
nearest neighbor can also--
it also looks up different input
points based on their features.
Nearest neighbor doesn't
learn to do this.
I still think it's cool
that we need to learn this
because it does
require a decent amount
of computational sequences
that we have to learn,
like match all the features,
look up target value,
copy it back, and so on.
But it is, in fact, very easy
for us to complicate this task
to a degree such
that, essentially,
no other model that we know
of can solve this very easily.
And so, a really
simple thing to do
is just to add a plus 1 to
all of the duplicate values.
So now, our nearest
neighbor would look up
the right row, of course,
but it would always
predict the wrong target
with a plus 1 on it.
And in fact, many of the
models that we're aware of,
they're not modeling
the joint distribution
over features and targets.
What they're modeling is
the conditional distribution
of the targets given
the input features.
So they also cannot do this.
And so, for us, it's
really no problem at all.
NPTs will just learn to subtract
another one and no problems.
And sure, this is also still
a very synthetic setting.
But I do think--
I mean, I challenge you
to come up with something
that NPTs can't solve but
the other models can solve.
I think this-- in general,
this masking mechanism
and the non-parametricity
of the approach
is really nice in general and
leads to lots of nice behavior
in a variety of settings.
And so, with that,
I think we can
go to the conclusions, which
Neil is going to give you.
Yeah, I think--
I mean, we can cut out
the main part here.
I'll just fast forward.
Just look at them.
Yeah, I was going
to say, I think
you got you all get the gist.
NPTs take the entire
data set as input
and they use self-attention
to model complex relationships
between data points.
They do well in
experiments on tabular data
as well as image data.
We present some of these
interventional experiments
to show that they can solve
complex reasoning tasks.
There are some more
experiments in the paper.
I'd say that the interesting
type of future work
is scaling type things.
So we can-- not having this
mini batching approximation.
And then, also just
trying to expand this
to some more interesting
application demands.
So we talked a little
bit about meta learning,
but it could also be things
like few shot generalization
in general, domain adaptation,
semi-supervised learning, et
cetera.
So I think if there's
some more questions, maybe
we can do some more discussion.
Yeah, sounds good.
Great.
Thanks for the talk.
I think everyone had a fun time.
So good.
[CLAPPING]
I will just also ask
some general questions.
And then, we can have
a discussion session
with everyone after that.
So I think one thing
that I noticed is this--
you said this is
similar to k-NNs.
And I thought this seems
similar to like graph neural
networks where you can think
each data point is like a node.
And then, you can
think of everything
as a fully connected graph.
And you're learning some sort
of attention rate in this graph.
So this is like
a node prediction
task you are kind of doing
on this graph structure.
So any comment on that?
Is it similar to
graph neural networks
or is it like other differences?
Yeah, that's a very
good observation.
Yeah, I think there are a
lot of similarities to work
done on graph neural networks.
If we want to talk
about differences,
the differences
might be that we're
kind of assuming a fully
connected graph, right?
And so, you could
maybe also phrase
that as we're discovering
the relational structure.
Whereas, graph neural networks
usually assume that it's given.
But that's also not always true.
And so, there are a
lot of similarities.
I don't know, Neil, if there
is something specific you would
like to mention, go ahead.
But it's a very
good observation.
And we also do feel
that that's the case.
And we've added an extra
section on related work
on geographical networks in the
updated version of the paper
that will be online soon.
Got it.
Yeah, I agree with
everything you've said.
I think that the closest work
from the GNN literature that we
were looking at a little bit
was this neural relational
inference paper, which uses
message passing neural networks
to try to learn edges that
may or may not exist and help
for extrapolating,
I think, positions
of particles in a multi-particle
system or something, which
is a similar idea to us.
If you don't have
these edges as given,
the attention
mechanism can kind of
approximate an
interesting relationship
amongst some interacting things.
I see.
Got it.
Yeah, that's really cool.
Another thing is-- so you
mostly look on tabular data.
But can you also
have other modalities
like if you want to do
language or something?
Can you still use
non-parametric transformers?
Yeah, so I think part of our
motivation for doing tabular
was because we felt like
tabular data is, in a sense,
a generalization of, let's say,
the language data, for example.
I mean, I guess there's these
other notions that people
have brought up like padding.
But ultimately,
you can think of it
as a bunch of
categorical attributes.
So it is definitely
generalizable to things
like sentences.
And we do images.
So yeah.
I think, actually, like--
I always go back and
forth on whether or not
I think smaller or larger data
is more interesting for us.
So I think small data
is really interesting
because we can just fit the
entire data set into it.
And all of this just
works out of the box
without any extra thought.
But large data is actually
also really interesting
because, sure, you
might have to introduce
some approximative mechanism
or some lookup mechanism
because you can't always
have the entire data set in.
But, at the same time, you
are very explicitly kind
of trading off the
compute that you
use to look up with the
compute that you need to store.
How many parameters in GPT
are used for storing data?
There's lots of memorization
happening in these models,
and we know that.
And so, maybe we can use the
parameters more efficiently
to learn lookup
type behavior that
is more close to this
neural k-NN or whatever.
So I think these are
very exciting questions.
Yeah.
I'll also be looking
forward to the future
because this seems
like a very good way
to do a one shot kind
of learning situations.
So really interesting
to see that.
OK, so I will stop
the recording and we
can have any other questions.